<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://abcsofdatascience.ca/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://abcsofdatascience.ca/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-03-30T10:23:30-05:00</updated><id>https://abcsofdatascience.ca/feed.xml</id><title type="html">ABCs of data science</title><subtitle>A gentle introduction to many data science concepts for readers of all backgrounds</subtitle><entry><title type="html">B is for Bias</title><link href="https://abcsofdatascience.ca/blog/b-is-for-bias" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="B is for Bias" /><published>2020-02-01T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-02-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://abcsofdatascience.ca/blog/b-is-for-bias</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abcsofdatascience.ca/blog/b-is-for-bias">&lt;p&gt;The term bias is used in a few different contexts within data science. When people mention bias they are typically referring to either the “bias-variance tradeoff” or “unjust bias”. I’ll primarily talk about unjust bias in this blog and will talk about tuning models/measuring model performance in later blogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bias-variance-tradeoff&quot;&gt;Bias-variance tradeoff&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bias%E2%80%93variance_tradeoff&quot;&gt;bias-variance tradeoff&lt;/a&gt; refers to tuning models such that they don’t under/overfit your data. A model has high bias if it underfits the training set (e.g. if you are trying to fit a line to non-linear data). A model has high variance if it overfits the training set (i.e. doesn’t generalize well). This could occur if you have a huge non-linear function with a large number of parameters. The bias-variance tradeoff is trying to find a model that minimizes both of these phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unjust-bias-and-the-importance-of-having-a-human-in-the-loop&quot;&gt;Unjust bias and the importance of having a human in the loop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning models are useful for helping humans sort through large piles of data. However, it is critical to have a human in the loop in order to validate predictions. It’s particularly important when ML models are used to predict things like university admissions or welfare benefits which have a huge impact on people’s lives. As we talked about in the previous blog, there are two key points to always keep in mind about AI/ML&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s not magic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s not perfect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problems arise when people treat the output of ML models as completely objective (or magic) with no opportunities to overrule these predictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bias refers to a model that is prejudiced in favour of particular categories. Unjust bias occurs when there is a mismatch between the models view of the world and how we think the world should be. There are many reasons that this can happen but two of the big ones are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The training data is not truly representative. It may favour certain categories over others leading to better predictions on those categories. As the saying goes: “garbage in, garbage out”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The training data is truly representative of past behaviour. However, this might be different than what we want the future behaviour to be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of famous examples of biased models which demonstrate this behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;facial-recognition&quot;&gt;Facial recognition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facial recognition tools are increasingly being utilized by organizations such as law enforcement agencies. Model fairness is critical in this case since if a model is biased against particular subgroups it will have a disproportionate impact on the lives of people in that subgroup.
Researchers studied 3 commercially available facial recognition tools from Microsoft, IBM, and FACE++ (study is &lt;a href=&quot;http://gendershades.org/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). The researchers found that the models performed much better on men and also had higher accuracy on lighter skinned people. In the worst case there was a 34.4% difference in accuracy between lighter skinned men compared to darker skinned women. This shows when the training data does not accurately represent all subgroups the result is a biased model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/b_is_for_bias/gendershades.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Taken from http://gendershages.org&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;amazons-hiring-model&quot;&gt;Amazon’s hiring model&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many companies, Amazon receives huge numbers of applicants and sorting through these applications is incredibly time intensive. They had a historical set of applications and know which of those candidates were hired. So, they developed a machine learning model to sort through the applications and rank the candidates in terms of their likelihood to be hired. However, this essentially turned into a gender detection model since the vast majority of their previous hires were men. For example, the model would penalize resumes which included the word “women’s”. This is a case where a model can make accurate predictions based on historical data, however this does not match with how hiring should be done. Despite the fact that Amazon scrapped this model, they are far from the only company who would like to automate portions of their hiring process. Creating a fair and unbiased method of doing so that is interpretable is still an open research question. You should be suspicious of anyone who claims to have solved this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/ai_hiring_algorithm.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;So glad Kate over in R&amp;amp;D pushed for using the AlgoMaxAnalyzer to look into this. Hiring her was a great decisio- waaaait.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-can-we-fix-this&quot;&gt;How can we fix this?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that &lt;strong&gt;humans are also biased&lt;/strong&gt;. They can grade using different criteria if they get grumpy or tired. The appeal of using ML models is that they are much cheaper than humans and can scale much better. If left unchecked, this just means that biased decisions are made at a much larger scale than what was done previously. The best approach is to use a mixture of ML models while keeping a human in the loop. This means providing a way for people to appeal decisions made by an ML model (such as university/college admissions) and allowing a human to override the decision. As researchers, something to keep in mind is that the users of these algorithms may not understand probabilities/confidence intervals. Even if they do understand these concepts they may not feel comfortable overruling the ML model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating models that are fair and interpretable is still an active area of research. This is an incredibly complex and nuanced topic but it is important to be aware of it. Later on, I will write a blog about the different techniques you can use to interpret ML models to try and gain insight into how they are making decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-resources&quot;&gt;Other resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=S-6YGPrmtYc&quot;&gt;Getting Specific About Algorithmic Bias&lt;/a&gt;) - &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/math_rachel&quot;&gt;Rachel Thomas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.ca/Weapons-Math-Destruction-Increases-Inequality/dp/0553418815&quot;&gt;Weapons of Math Destruction&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mathbabedotorg&quot;&gt;Cathy O’Neil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.ca/Hello-World-Algorithms-Define-Future/dp/039363499X&quot;&gt;Hello World&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/fryrsquared&quot;&gt;Hannah Fry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The term bias is used in a few different contexts within data science. When people mention bias they are typically referring to either the “bias-variance tradeoff” or “unjust bias”. I’ll primarily talk about unjust bias in this blog and will talk about tuning models/measuring model performance in later blogs.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A is for Artificial Intelligence</title><link href="https://abcsofdatascience.ca/blog/a-is-for-ai" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A is for Artificial Intelligence" /><published>2020-01-15T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-01-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>https://abcsofdatascience.ca/blog/a-is-for-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abcsofdatascience.ca/blog/a-is-for-ai">&lt;p&gt;I was recently in San Francisco and throughout the city there are many, many billboards containing slogans like “Mission Critical AI” and “Enterprise AI”. There is no doubt that usage of the phrase “artificial intelligence” or AI has increased dramatically in recent years. This increased usage has made it difficult to tell what “using AI” even means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-what-is-ai&quot;&gt;So what is AI?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people have differing opinions on how to strictly define AI. When people refer to AI this is generally synonymous with machine learning (ML). Since it’s so hard to come up with a definition, let’s define what AI is not:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI is not magic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI is not perfect (more on that in B is for Bias)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to come up with a strict definition for AI since the generally agreed upon definition has evolved over time. In the 1980s people called large rule based systems (“expert systems”) AI. These systems required subject matter experts and programmers to define a set of rules. As you can imagine (or remember) this is a very time intensive process and there are lots of edge cases to consider. Nowadays people typically think of deep learning (more on that in D is for Deep Learning) as AI. This requires lots of labeled training data (which often needs to be labeled by experts) but models can learn their own rules about the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both cases the “intelligence” part of AI is a bit of a misnomer. Another term that has been suggested  is &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/fchollet/status/1214392496375025664&quot;&gt;“cognitive automation”&lt;/a&gt;. We are trying to teach a machine to perform a set of tasks based on our knowledge of the world. This is different from something that is truly intelligent that can reason about the world and learn abstract concepts. This distinction is important and referred to as “general” versus “narrow” AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General AI (also referred to as strong AI) refers to a machine that is “human-like” (think HAL 9000 or Skynet). As you would expect from the name, it can generalize it’s previous knowledge to new problem domains. This means that It can intelligently perform a wide variety of tasks without needing explicit training data. Voice assistants like Alexa, and Siri seem like they can generalize, but as anyone who has used them knows, they definitely have limits. They tend not to understand context in a way that a human would, and questions may need to be rephrased in order to be interpreted correctly. A true general AI doesn’t currently exist and it will probably be a while before it does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Narrow AI (or weak AI) refers to a machine that is good at specific tasks (e.g. image recognition) but can’t generalize to different domains. For example, you could train a machine learning model to distinguish between cats and dogs but it would not be able to answer the question “Where is the best pizza in Ottawa?”. Narrow AI works by using predefined rules or learning from lots of (probably labelled) data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-ai-used-for&quot;&gt;What is AI used for?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI/ML is widely used in a large variety of industries for a number of tasks. This includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recommending videos on youtube&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Detecting if a computer has malware&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financial trading&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helping doctors make diagnoses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Voice assistants like Google Assistant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these tasks are applications of fields such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Computer vision (processing images and audio)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Natural Language Processing (NLP)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recommender systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that AI is a buzzword means that it is applied to many different products (even if they don’t include any ML models). This over usage of the term causes many people to twitch when they hear it (and judge people who do use the term). However, it’s important to keep in mind your audience when you are talking about machine learning. Some audiences may not be familiar with specific technical terms (point them at this blog series ;) ) but have heard the term AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI/ML is a rapidly growing field which is being applied to a large variety of domains. It’s hard to separate what is real from the snake oil. I’m hoping this blog series will give you enough background knowledge to think critically when you hear the term AI and know the limitations of AI/ML models. In the next blog I’ll talk about many of these limitations and how they affect people’s everyday lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-resources&quot;&gt;Other resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL8dPuuaLjXtO65LeD2p4_Sb5XQ51par_b&quot;&gt;Crash Course Artificial Intelligence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.ca/Hello-World-Algorithms-Define-Future/dp/039363499X&quot;&gt;Hello World&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/fryrsquared&quot;&gt;Hannah Fry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I was recently in San Francisco and throughout the city there are many, many billboards containing slogans like “Mission Critical AI” and “Enterprise AI”. There is no doubt that usage of the phrase “artificial intelligence” or AI has increased dramatically in recent years. This increased usage has made it difficult to tell what “using AI” even means.</summary></entry></feed>